Niccolò Ajroldi



BIOGRAPHY

My background is in mathematics and statistics, and their application to machine learning. My research focuses on optimization for deep learning and novel sequence modeling architectures. I am particularly interested in benchmarking optimization algorithms for training large language models, enhancing performance and efficiency. I very much enjoy developing machine learning codebases!

EXPERIENCE

Research Engineer - Max Planck Institute for Intelligent Systems, Ellis Institute Tübingen

Tübingen, DE

Jan. 2023 - Ongoing

- Research on novel sequence model architectures and optimization algorithms with Jonas Geiping and Antonio Orvieto.
- Developed submissions to AlgoPerf, a benchmark for optimization algorithms, scoring third in the competition leaderboard.
- · Joined MLCommons Algorithmic Efficiency team, developed open-source contributions to AlgoPerf API.
- Mentored research interns in the CaCTüS program, researching LLM optimization and LLM watermarking.
- Released a simple PyTorch <u>codebase</u> for pretraining modern language models.

Al Resident - Meta, FAIR Labs

Seattle, WA

July 2022 - Aug. 2023

- Research on hypergradient methods for adaptive hyperparameter tuning with Lin Xiao.
- Investigated loss spikes in language model optimization and the Slingshot phenomenon.
- · Gained experience in ML optimization, distributed training, and familiarity with vision and language models.

ML Researcher - U-Care Medical

♥Turin, IT

Dec. 2021 - June 2022

- Developed machine learning models to forecast Acute Kidney Injury in critically ill patients.
- Developed algorithms to discriminate persistent kidney injury and transient kidney injury in ICU patients.
- Conducted statistical analyses and designed data visualization APIs to support product promotion.

EDUCATION

Politecnico di Milano - Master of Science in Mathematical Engineering & Statistical Learning

Mar. 2019 - Oct. 2021

- Thesis: Functional Time Series Forecasting.
- · Advisor: Simone Vantini.
- Teaching assistant for "Algorithms and Parallel Computing", covering C++, OOP, data structures, parallel programming.

Politecnico di Milano - Bachelor of Science in Mathematical Engineering

Oct. 2015 - Mar. 2019

- Thesis: <u>Deep Learning Optimization Algorithms and Saddle Points</u>.
- · Advisor: Danilo Ardagna.

PUBLICATIONS

Islamov, R., Ajroldi, N., Orvieto, A., & Lucchi, A. (2024). Loss landscape characterization of neural networks without over-parametrization. To appear in Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 2024 (NeurIPS 2024). ArXiv preprint.

Ajroldi, N., Diquigiovanni, J., Fontana, M., & Vantini, S. (2023). Conformal prediction bands for two-dimensional functional time series. Computational Statistics & Data Analysis (CSDA), 187, 107821. Article URL.

Alfieri, F., Ancona, A., Tripepi, G., Rubeis, A., Ajroldi, N., Finazzi, S., Cauda, V., & Fagugli, R. M. (2023). Continuous and early prediction of future moderate and severe acute kidney injury in critically ill patients. PLOS ONE, 18, 1–22. <u>Article URL</u>.